<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content"><channel><title>Ryan Budish</title><description>Technologist, Lawyer, Developer</description><link>https://ryanbudish.com</link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 31 Jan 2021 14:49:03 -0500</lastBuildDate><pubDate>Sun, 31 Jan 2021 14:49:03 -0500</pubDate><ttl>250</ttl><atom:link href="https://ryanbudish.com/feed.rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><guid isPermaLink="true">https://ryanbudish.com/displacer/Displacer</guid><title>Displacer for MacOS</title><description></description><link>https://ryanbudish.com/displacer/Displacer</link><pubDate>Sun, 31 Jan 2021 14:46:10 -0500</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2>Now Available for MacOS</h2><img src="https://ryanbudish.com/images/posts/displacersite2.jpg" alt="Displacer Screenshots"/><h2><a href="https://apps.apple.com/us/app/displacer/id1549469449?mt=12&itsct=apps_box&itscg=30200"><img src="https://ryanbudish.com/images/posts/AppleStoreWhite.svg" alt="Displacer on the App Store"/></a></h2><p>Displacer makes it easy to switch between multiple monitor configurations.<br><br>MacOS is great at remembering your monitor arrangements when you're switching between different monitors -- but what if you use the same displays in different configurations? Before Displacer your only options were either using complicated command line scripts or opening up System Preferences and dragging your displays around... every single time.</p><p>Displacer is a small menu bar utility that lets you easily save your monitor configurations and quickly switch between them. No more hunting through System Preferences every time you move your laptop around your desk.</p><p>Setting up Displacer is simple:</p><ol><li>Open Displacer</li><li>Set your monitor arrangement in System Preferences -&gt; Displays -&gt; Arrangement</li><li>Press the big + button in Displacer</li></ol><p>That's it! Your arrangement is now saved. You can repeat for up to three different monitor arrangements.</p><p>When you need to switch, just open Displacer and click a saved configuration. Displacer detects when and which monitors are attached and removed, so you can only switch to a configuration that matches the available monitors.</p><h3>Example</h3><p>Lucy has a sit/stand desk at home. When she's sitting, her monitor is above her laptop. But when she's standing, she moves her laptop to the right of her monitor. Because it's the same monitor, MacOS doesn't know when she's moved her laptop below or next to her monitor. Displacer lets Lucy save her two configurations, and easily switch between them when she moves between sitting and standing. And when Lucy goes to her office and connects to different monitors, Displacer will automatically detect that her saved configurations don't work for her office and disable those options.</p><h2><a href="https://apps.apple.com/us/app/displacer/id1549469449?mt=12&itsct=apps_box&itscg=30200"><img src="https://ryanbudish.com/images/posts/AppleStoreWhite.svg" alt="Displacer on the App Store"/></a></h2>]]></content:encoded></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">https://ryanbudish.com/about/aboutme</guid><title>About</title><description></description><link>https://ryanbudish.com/about/aboutme</link><pubDate>Sun, 31 Jan 2021 14:46:10 -0500</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I recently started a new job as a Privacy &amp; Public Policy Manager at Facebook, where I work on issues relating to data portability and automated decision making.</p><p>Priort to that, I spent nearly 10 years at at the <a href="https://cyber.harvard.edu">Berkman Klein Center for Internet &amp; Society at Harvard University</a>, where I was the Assistant Director for Research and led some of the Center's work on the ethics and governance of artificial intelligence, online censorship, Internet governance, and more.</p><p>I'm a recovering lawyer, oft-injured runner, and father to two wonderful girls. In my spare time, I'm a mostly self-taught iOS app developer who plays around with Swift and SwiftUI.</p><p>My words and work on this site are my own, and do not represent the views of anyone else.</p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">https://ryanbudish.com/words/2020-11-29-getting-unstuck</guid><title>Getting Unstuck (and becoming an app developer)</title><description>Describing the launch of my new app--Unstuck--and the process of becoming an app developer</description><link>https://ryanbudish.com/words/2020-11-29-getting-unstuck</link><pubDate>Sun, 29 Nov 2020 16:00:00 -0500</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A few days ago I released <a href="https://apps.apple.com/us/app/unstuck-coaching-for-growth/id1494636077?itsct=apps_box&itscg=30200">Unstuck to the iOS App Store</a>. Because of that, and in honor of Thanksgiving, I wanted to share a few of the things that I'm thankful for that made this possible.</p><p>+++</p><p>It seems weird to call myself an "independent app developer," but my app is live, and I've even had some early adopters (Hi Mom!). So I guess that qualifies me for the indy app developer club.[^1] If you want to learn more about the app, I've shared plenty of details <a href="https://ryanbudish.com/unstuck">here</a>. But here I wanted to share a few of the things that made this possible.</p><h2>Teaching Myself?</h2><p>A few people have asked me, "how did you learn to make this app?" And the easy answer is, "I taught myself." And to some extent that is true. I never took a class on <a href="https://developer.apple.com/xcode/swiftui/">SwiftUI</a>--a new framework from Apple for designing user interfaces that looked clean and native, with simple code that could scale across devices. No one ever taught me how to get an app into the App Store. And I've spent countless hours reading articles, tutorials, watching instructional videos and more. But at the same time, saying that "I taught myself" ignores the foundation that I was starting from.</p><p>Growing up, I loved computers and technology. So it was an easy decision in college to study computer science. For someone who was terrible at art and wasn't crafty or handy, it was magical to be able to transform a blank screen into a program that could actually <em>do</em> something. Around 2003-2004, my area of focus in CS was artificial intelligence and robotics, creating neural network brains that could help robots solve mazes and complete tasks. In another life, perhaps I would have had the foresight to go to graduate school in AI, and today I'd be a billionaire.</p><p>But in the early 2000s, we were still in the throws of the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/AI_winter">AI winter</a>, I dreamed of a career in politics, and I thought I was a better writer than I was a programmer. So I went to law school instead.[^2] But I never stopped loving the act of creation through code.</p><p>When it came to programming, I became a dabbler. I would buy books. I would sign up for (and sometimes complete) online courses.[^3] And even took an iOS development course at the <a href="https://www.extension.harvard.edu">Harvard Extension School</a>. As a result, I was able to teach myself some of the things I needed to know to make Unstuck, because I was never starting from scratch. Learning Swift, for example, isn't so hard when you've also learned C, Java, Python and LISP. Learning SwiftUI isn't so hard when you already know other frameworks for iOS development. So I'm thankful for the foundation I've been able to build that made Unstuck possible. I'm not an expert developer by any stretch of the imagination, but the experiences I've had over the past 20 years made it possible for me to move from concept to reality.</p><h2>Inspirational Colleagues</h2><p>I'm not an expert on peer coaching. In fact, up until recently, I had never even heard of it. A couple of years ago, my office brought in a leadership training coach, <a href="https://www.leadershipgrowthsolutions.com/about-1">Nancy Persson</a>, who along with <a href="https://hls.harvard.edu/faculty/directory/11766/Fjeld">Jessica Fjeld</a> from Harvard Law School's Cyberlaw Clinic, created a series of workshops for the senior staff at the Center. One of the things that they taught us in these workshops was an incredibly impactful method of thinking through problems: peer coaching.[^4]</p><p>As Nancy and Jess taught it, peer coaching required three people: (1) the person sharing their challenge; (2) the coach; and (3) a facilitator to keep track of the time. At the end of one of our trainings, a colleague raised their hand and asked "if you couldn't get find three people, could you do peer coaching with two people?" Nancy said that it could be done with two people, but having three allows the coach and the learner to focus on the discussion. It was that question that got me thinking about whether an app could help.</p><p>But Nancy and Jess did more than just provide the initial inspiration for the app. They were critical (in every sense of the word) advisors along the way. They allowed me to draw on the materials they had created for the workshop, offered advice on the application, and even participated as testers of the early versions of the app.</p><h2>90% Done, 90% Remaining</h2><p>Every year the University closes between Christmas and New Years. And in 2019, I was traveling with my wife's family for the holidays. The evenings were quiet, so every night after we put the kids down to bed, I'd open up my laptop, fire up Xcode and start the process of making something out of nothing. Starting projects is easy. At the beginning I could focus on the low-hanging fruit and solving some of the simple challenges. By early January, I had a working prototype. It was very rough, and it was missing several key features, but it essentially worked.</p><p>There's an <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ninety-ninety_rule">old saying</a> in computer science: "The first 90 percent of the code accounts for the first 90 percent of the development time. The remaining 10 percent of the code accounts for the other 90 percent of the development time." Yes, I had a functional app by January, but in many ways the work was just getting started. Of course, there were features to add, and bugs to fix. But beyond the core functionality of the app itself, there were also many other components that had to be created. I needed to make the icon, the launch screen, write the text for the App Store descriptions, create screenshots for the App Store (in four different sizes for four different devices), and a thousand other little things you might never realize go into creating an app.</p><p>Once back in the grind of day-to-day life, progress became slow. A more skilled or full-time programmer would have made quick work of this app. But for me, with a full time job, two kids, and learning as I went[^5], I had to make the most of the limited time I had. Late evenings, nap times, and stolen moments here and there, became my development time. No one was more helpful in moving this app from dream to reality than my wife. Beyond just encouragement, she would occasionally take the kids out of the house for the day, so I could have hours of uninterrupted work time. Without that support, I never would have made progress. And over the last couple of months, she urged me (sometimes strongly) to push the app over the finish line.</p><h2>Looking Ahead</h2><p>I'm not going to get rich off this app. In fact, I may never break even on my Apple Developer annual fee--the $99 annual fee just for the privilege of being able to submit an app to the App Store. But that was never the point. I'm incredibly proud that I got this done, and I'm proud that I can say I'm an "app developer." Now, onto the next app...</p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">https://ryanbudish.com/unstuck/Unstuck</guid><title>Unstuck - Coaching for Growth</title><description></description><link>https://ryanbudish.com/unstuck/Unstuck</link><pubDate>Wed, 25 Nov 2020 16:38:00 -0500</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2>Now Available for iOS and iPadOS!</h2><img src="https://ryanbudish.com/images/posts/unstucksite.jpg" alt="Unstuck Screenshots"/><h2><a href="https://apps.apple.com/us/app/unstuck-coaching-for-growth/id1494636077?itsct=apps_box&itscg=30200"><img src="https://ryanbudish.com/images/posts/AppleStoreWhite.svg" alt="Unstuck on the App Store"/></a></h2><p>Just released to the App Store, Unstuck is a new and simple tool to help you break through difficult interpersonal, management, substantive, and organizational challenges. Unstuck guides you through the process of peer coaching -- a proven approach to collaboratively solving problems. This app supports that process by providing structure, suggesting helpful coaching questions, and guiding you toward new perspectives and insights that will help you overcome whatever challenges you're facing.</p><h3>What is peer coaching?</h3><p>Peer coaching is a widely used framework in organizations, schools, and workplaces, as a way to collaboratively find solutions when facing a difficult challenge. In a two-person coaching session, one person is the learner -- the person seeking a fresh perspective on a challenge. The other person is the coach -- someone who listens and asks probing, helpful questions.</p><p>Unstuck guides you through the three stages of peer coaching: 1) The learner describes the "what, where, when, and who" of their challenge so that the coach understands the situation; 2) The coach asks questions to help the learner talk through the problem and expand their thinking; 3) Both the learner and the coach have an opportunity to reflect on what they've learned.</p><p>Unstuck leads you through these stages by tracking the time, prompting you to move on to the next stage, and even offering questions to consider. This allows you to focus on the coaching.</p><h3>Why use peer coaching?</h3><p>Peer coaching can help you see new approaches to difficult personal, workplace, or social challenges. But peer coaching can help in other ways, too! According to research in the Journal of Applied Behavioral Science, peer coaching can help heighten self-awareness, improve active listening skills, enhance interpersonal connections, and improve leadership skills. This is why peer coaching is taught in leadership and management training programs around the world.</p><h3>How do I get started?</h3><p>It's easy to get started. All you need to do is find a trusted friend or colleague willing to be your coach. Their job is to help you think through the challenge by listening and asking thoughtful questions, not giving advice or telling you what to do. Customize your Unstuck session to fit your schedule. Whether you have an hour or only 10 minutes to talk with your coach, Unstuck will help you make the most of whatever time that you have.</p><h3>Can I use Unstuck on my own?</h3><p>Yes! Unstuck is primarily designed to help two people do peer coaching together (in person or remotely). But by using Unstuck's built-in question library, you can be your own coach and think through challenges on your own.</p><h3>Do I need special training?</h3><p>No! Unstuck makes it easy to begin peer coaching. Neither the learner nor the coach needs any kind of special training or expertise -- just a willingness to listen and think. And if the coach gets stuck, Unstuck can suggest questions!</p><h2><a href="https://apps.apple.com/us/app/unstuck-coaching-for-growth/id1494636077?itsct=apps_box&itscg=30200"><img src="https://ryanbudish.com/images/posts/AppleStoreWhite.svg" alt="Unstuck on the App Store"/></a></h2>]]></content:encoded></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">https://ryanbudish.com/words/2020-10-23-austin-mann-review</guid><title>Austin Mann's iPhone 12 Review</title><description>I always love Austin Mann's iPhone reviews. Clearly the new cameras are great, but these reviews demonstrate that good photographers--not good cameras--take good photos.  All the most expensive gear in the world, and I couldn't take photos as good as he gets from a phone.</description><link>https://ryanbudish.com/words/2020-10-23-austin-mann-review</link><pubDate>Fri, 23 Oct 2020 22:27:00 -0400</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I always love Austin Mann's iPhone reviews. Clearly the new cameras are great, but these reviews demonstrate that good photographers--not good cameras--take good photos. All the most expensive gear in the world, and I couldn't take photos as good as he gets from a phone.</p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">https://ryanbudish.com/words/2020-10-23-political-agendas</guid><title>Political Agendas</title><description>In his 60 Minutes interview last week, President Trump expressed doubts about the scientific evidence of climate change, saying "You'd have to show me the scientists because they have a very big political agenda...."</description><link>https://ryanbudish.com/words/2020-10-23-political-agendas</link><pubDate>Fri, 23 Oct 2020 08:00:00 -0400</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In his 60 Minutes interview last week, President Trump <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2018/10/15/media/reliable-sources-10-14-18/index.html">expressed doubts</a> about the scientific evidence of climate change, saying "You'd have to show me the scientists because they have a very big political agenda...."</p><p>+++</p><p>There are clearly powerful interests on the other side who fight efforts to curb greenhouse gas emissions. The oil, gas, coal, and automobile manufacturers all have huge economic incentives to deny climate change. And they spend a lot of money to advance that political agenda.<br><br>But what political agenda does Trump think those climate scientists are advancing? Does he imagine that "Big Solar" has bankrolled tens of thousands of scientists over the last 30 years all in an effort to slowly drive oil companies out of business through mildly intrusive regulations? Or maybe he thinks these scientists just grew up hating coal so much that they dedicated their lives to getting multiple advanced degrees, and in relatively low-paying academic jobs, just so they could someday fabricate evidence about climate change?</p><p>The belief that climate change is just part of a scientific conspiracy is entirely circular. I don't know anyone who hates coal, or oil, or cars out of spite. People don't like them because science has demonstrated their negative environmental impacts. Those who believe in the conspiracy must believe that climate scientists produce fake scientific evidence, which in turn creates a generation of people concerned about the environment, some of whom become scientists who themselves go on to produce more fake evidence, continuing the cycle. Why would anyone go through all that trouble?</p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">https://ryanbudish.com/words/2020-10-18-the-original-sin</guid><title>The Original Sin</title><description>Following Justice Ginsburg's death a few weeks ago, there's been a lot of hand-wringing around the so-called "McConnell Rule" regarding not confirming Supreme Court justices during an election year.  This "rule" was invoked in early 2016, when Senator Mitch McConnell refused to hold a vote on President Obama's selection of Judge Merrick Garland to fill Justice Scalia's seat.</description><link>https://ryanbudish.com/words/2020-10-18-the-original-sin</link><pubDate>Sun, 18 Oct 2020 21:42:00 -0400</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Following Justice Ginsburg's death a few weeks ago, there's been a lot of hand-wringing around the so-called <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/2020/09/18/why-mitch-mcconnell-intends-confirm-new-supreme-court-justice-now-when-he-wouldnt-2016/">"McConnell Rule"</a> regarding not confirming Supreme Court justices during an election year. This "rule" was invoked in early 2016, when Senator Mitch McConnell refused to hold a vote on President Obama's selection of Judge Merrick Garland to fill Justice Scalia's seat.</p><p>+++</p><p>Calling this a rule, however, was always silly. It was never anything more than an excuse for the naked exercise of power (even if such an exercise of power flew in the face of long-standing norms and precedent). The unenforceability of the rule was apparent in 2016. What constitutes an election year? January of an election year? 365 days before an election? When the first exploratory campaign paperwork is filed with FEC? Should a second-term President ever be allowed to fill a Supreme Court vacancy? There was never any attempt to answer such questions, because the goal was political expediency, not enforceability or logic.<br><br>And yet Democrats persisted in the delusion that if a vacancy opened up in the final year of Trump's first term, surely Mitch McConnell--man of his word that he is--would surely be bound by his own precedent. After all, what good is a rule if it is not applied in an even-handed and fair manner? But now on the precipice of what will almost certainly be the confirmation of Judge Amy Coney Barrett less than 16 days before the 2020 election, Democrats feel enraged as all pretense of principle has been stripped away, leaving bare the naked political ambition that was at the core all along.</p><p>Democrats (and I am one) should feel enraged. But at what? What was the original sin of our current Supreme Court predicament? Should we be upset that Mitch McConnell is not following the imaginary rule he created four years ago? As much as it saddens me that Donald Trump gets to dramatically alter the balance of power on the Supreme Court--something which will have <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2020/10/05/us/politics/thomas-alito-same-sex-marriage.html">lasting, negative effects</a> for at least a generation--the President has every right to fill that seat with a nominee of his choosing. Democratic claims of hypocrisy are based either on the belief that the McConnell rule is in fact a rule or on the belief that the person who created the rule should be bound by it. In either case, being upset that McConnell is trying to fill Justice Ginsburg's seat mere days before an election legitimizes and validates a practice that was wrong four years ago.</p><p>In that case, was the original sin the creation of the McConnell rule in the first place? Just as Donald Trump should get to fill Justice Ginsburg's seat days before the election that could replace him, Barack Obama should have been able to fill Justice Scalia's seat when Justice Scalia passed away 266 days before the election. Despite Mitch McConnell's weak attempts at justification at the time, there is nothing in the Constitution or the country's 240 year history that suggested otherwise. The McConnell rule was a <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2016/02/16/opinion/in-election-years-a-history-of-confirming-court-nominees.html">norm shattering</a> act of creative fiction. Democrats should have been enraged. Many were, but I suspect hubris tempered the reaction for many.</p><p>In the months leading up to the 2016 election, it was hard for many to imagine anything other than Hillary Clinton winning. This was more than just wishful thinking; on October 26--12 days before the election--one national poll[^1] had <a href="https://time.com/4546942/hillary-clinton-donald-trump-lead-poll/">Hillary ahead by 14% points</a>. For many Democrats, it seemed like filling Justice Scalia's seat was <em>fait accompli.</em> Hillary would win in November and would appoint Judge Garland or an equally qualified jurist, and engaging in parliamentary tactics to force a nomination through earlier would risk energizing conservative voters (in much the same way that Ginsburg's death has <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2020/sep/21/democrats-fundraising-records-ruth-bader-ginsburg-death">activated Democratic voters</a> this year). I think it was this hubris that prevented Democrats from being as angry as they should have been in 2016.</p><p>Although Democrats should have been more furious in 2016, this predicament did not start then. To understand the real problem, we have to look back even further--at the entirety of Obama's presidency. According to <a href="https://www.pewresearch.org/fact-tank/2020/07/15/how-trump-compares-with-other-recent-presidents-in-appointing-federal-judges/">Pew Research</a>, During his eight years in office, President Obama appointed 312 judges to the federal bench. During three-and-a-half years, President Trump has appointed 194. The differences are more stark when you compare their records at same point in their terms: <img src="https://ryanbudish.com/images/posts/trumpJudges.png"/></p><p>This difference was no accident. It was part of an <a href="https://www.brookings.edu/blog/fixgov/2018/06/04/senate-obstructionism-handed-judicial-vacancies-to-trump/">intentional campaign</a> to hold open judicial vacancies until a Republican president was sworn in.</p><blockquote><p>Just as it refused to consider Merrick Garland’s Supreme Court nomination, it shut down the lower court confirmation process. That’s water under the bridge. But documenting how the 114th Senate ratcheted up the contentiousness and polarization of an already broken confirmation process suggests how much harder it will be to ratchet it back into something with more comity and bipartisanship. Senate Majority Leader Mitch McConnell now insists that there’s nothing “we can do …that’s more important … than confirming judges as rapidly as we get them.”</p></blockquote><p>This situation did not start with Donald Trump or Merrick Garland. It was part of a years-long effort to politicize the courts. When Democrats float the idea of <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/2020/10/16/tricky-politics-court-packing-joe-biden/">"packing the court"</a> the GOP accuses them of politicizing the courts[^2]. The Democrats, in response need to make it clear that the original sin of politicizing the courts--whenever it started--certainly did not begin with court packing.</p>]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>